<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Articles to be enquired in the visitation, in the firste yere of the raigne of our moste dread soueraigne lady, Elizabeth by the grace of God, of Englande, Fraunce, and Irelande, Queene, defendour of the faith. &amp;c. Anno. 1559.</title>
            <title>Visitation articles. 1559</title>
            <author>Church of England.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1562</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 16 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00125</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10120</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120521</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855717</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855717</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21219</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00125)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21219)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 422:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Articles to be enquired in the visitation, in the firste yere of the raigne of our moste dread soueraigne lady, Elizabeth by the grace of God, of Englande, Fraunce, and Irelande, Queene, defendour of the faith. &amp;c. Anno. 1559.</title>
                  <title>Visitation articles. 1559</title>
                  <author>Church of England.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1558-1603 : Elizabeth I)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Richard Jugge, and John Cawood,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1562?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint and suggested publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>In title: 'enquired .. firste yere' (as in STC 10119); A2r last line: 'cupation.' and A3r line 15 ends: 'their'--Cf. STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B³.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; lacks B3.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Visitations, Ecclesiastical --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="modern_bookplate">
            <pb facs="tcp:21219:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> LIBER WILLIELMI MASKELL CLERICI</head>
                  <figDesc>bookplate of William Maskell bearing the monogram W M</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21219:1"/>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21219:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21219:2"/>
            <p>¶ Articles to be enquired in the viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in the firſte yere of the raigne of our moſte dread So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne Lady, Elizabeth by the grace of GOD, of Englande, Fraunce, and Irelande, Queene, defendour of the faith. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Anno. 1559.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="articles_of_visitation">
            <pb facs="tcp:21219:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21219:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>ARTICLES.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Yrſt,<note place="margin">1 Reſidencie.</note> whether any Parſon, Vicar, or Curate, be reſide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t continually vpon his Benefice, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng his duetie in preachyng, redyng and duelye mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtryng the holye Sacramentes.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">2 Falſe mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles.</note> whether in their Churches and Chappelles, all Images, Shrynes, all Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, Candelſtickes, Trindelles, or rolles of war, pictures, payntynges, and all other monumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of fayned and falſe miracles, pylgrymages, Idolatrye, and ſuperſtition, be remoued, aboly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">3 Lordes prayer.</note> whether they do not euery Holydaye when they haue no Sermon, immediatly after the Goſpell, openly, playnely, and diſtinctly, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyte to theyr paryſhioners in the Pulpitte, the Lordes prayer, the beliefe, and the tenne Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes in Englyſhe.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">4 To bryng vp youth.</note> whether they do charge fathers and mothers, maiſters, and gouernours of youth, to bryng them vp in ſome vertuous ſtudye and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupation.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21219:4"/>
Item,<note place="margin">5 Curates.</note> whether ſuche beneficed menne as be lawfully abſent from their benefices, do leaue theyr cures to a rude and vnlearned Parſon, and not to an honeſt well learned and expert Curate whiche can and wyll teache you holſome doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">6 Reatyng the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</note> whether they do diſcourage any perſon from readyng of any part of the Byble, eyther in Latin or Englyſhe, and do not rather comfort and exhort euery perſon to reade the ſame at con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient tymes, as the very lyuely worde of God, and the ſpeciall foode of mans ſoule.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">7 Tauernes and games.</note> whether Parſons, Vicars, Curates, and other Miniſters, be common haunters and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorters to Tauernes or Alehouſes, geuyng them ſelues to drynkyng, ryotyng, and playing at vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull games, and do not occupy them ſelues in the reading or hearing of ſome part of holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or in ſome other godly exerciſe.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">8 Preachers.</note> whether they haue admitted any man to preache in theyr cures, not beyng lawefullye licenced therevnto, or haue ben licenced accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyngly.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">9 Superſtitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </note> whether they vſe to declare to theyr paryſhioners any thyng to the extollyng or ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng forth of vayne and ſuperſtitious religion, pylgrimages, reliques, or ymages, or lyghtyng
<pb facs="tcp:21219:4"/>of candelles, kyſſyng, kneelyng, or deckyng of the ſame ymages.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">10 Regiſter.</note> whether they haue one booke or Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter kepte, wherein they wryte the day of euery weddyng, chriſtenyng, and burying.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">11 Obedience.</note> whether they haue exhorted the people to obedience to the Queenes Maieſtie, and mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and to charitie and loue one to another.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">12 The Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> whether they haue admonyſhed theyr paryſhioners, that they ought not to preſume to receyue the Sacrament of the body and bloud of Chriſte, before they can ſaye perfectly the Lordes prayer, the articles of the fayth, and the ten com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes in Englyſhe.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">13 Hoſpitalitie</note> whether they be reſident vppon their benefices, and kepe hoſpitalitie, or no. And yf they be abſent and kepe no hoſpitalitie, whether they do relieue their pariſhioners, and what they geue them.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">14 Reparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> whether Proprietaries. Parſons, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cars, and Clarkes, hauyng Churches, Chappels, and Manſions, do kepe theyr Chauncels, Recto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Vicarages, and all other houſes appertay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng to them, in due reparations.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">15 Prayer in Englyſhe.</note> whether they do counſayle or moue theyr pariſhioners rather to praye in a tongue not knowen, then in Englyſhe, or put theyr
<pb facs="tcp:21219:5"/>truſt in any certayne number of prayers, as in ſaying ouer a number of Beades,<note place="margin">Beades.</note> or other lyke.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">16 Diffamed perſons.</note> whether they haue receyued any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to the Communion, beyng openly knowen to be out of charitie with theyr neyghbours, or diffamed with any notorious cryme, and not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourmed.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">17 Pooremens boxe.</note> whether they haue prouided and haue a ſtrong Cheſt for the poore mens boxe, and ſet and faſtened the ſame in a place of the Churche moſt conuenient.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">18 Teſtamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.</note> whether they haue diligently called vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, exhorted, and moued theyr pariſſioners, and eſpecially when they make theyr teſtamentes, to geue to the ſayd poore mens boxe, and to beſtowe that vpon the poore,<note place="margin">Pooremens boxe.</note> whiche they were wont to beſtowe vpon pylgrimages, pardons, trentalles, and vpon other lyke blynde deuotions.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">19 Sicke. Buriall.</note> whether they haue denyed to viſite the ſicke, or burye the dead, beyng brought to the Churche.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">20 Symonie.</note> whether they haue bought theyr bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, or come to them by fraude, guyle, deceipt, or ſimonie.</p>
            <p>Item, whether they haue geuen open moni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to theyr pariſhioners,<note place="margin">21 Adulterers.</note> to detect and preſent
<pb facs="tcp:21219:5"/>to theyr Ordinarie, all adulterers, and fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, and ſuch men as haue two wyues lyuying, within theyr paryſhes.</p>
            <p>Item, whether they haue moniſhed theyr pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhioners openly, that they ſhould not ſell, geue,<note place="margin">22 Churche goodes.</note> nor otherwyſe alienate anye of theyr Churche goodes.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">23 Many bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices.</note> whether they or any of them do kepe mo benefices and other Eccleſiaſticall promoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, then they ought to do, not hauyng ſufficient licences and diſpenſations therevnto, and howe many they be, and theyr names.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">24 Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion</note> whether they miniſter the holye Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion any otherwyſe, then onlye after ſuche fourme and maner as it is ſet forth by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon aucthoritie of the Queenes Maieſtie and the Parliament.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">25 Letters of the word or preachyng.</note> whether you knowe any perſon with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in your paryſhe, or els where, that is a letter of the worde of God to be read in Englyſhe, or ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely preached in place and times conuenient.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">26 Goers out of the Churche.</note> whether in the tyme of the Letanye, or any other common prayer, in the tyme of the Sermon or Homylye, and when the Prieſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the Scriptures to the paryſhioners, any perſon haue departed out of the Churche, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out iuſte and neceſſarye cauſe, or diſturbe the
<pb facs="tcp:21219:6"/>Miniſter otherwyſe.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">27 Churche money.</note> whether the money commyng and ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng of any cattell or other moueable ſtockes of the Church, and money geuen and bequeathed to the fyndyng of torches, lyghtes, tapers, or lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes, not payde out of any landes, haue not ben employed to the poore mens cheſte.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">28 Kepers of the Church money.</note> who hath the ſayde ſtockes and money in theyr handes, and what be theyr names.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">29 Contempt of Prieſtes.</note> whether any indiſcrete perſons do vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitably comtemne and abuſe Prieſtes &amp; Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſters of the Churche.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">30 The kinges Grammer.</note> whether there be any other Grammer taught in any ſcoole within this Dioceſſe, then that which is ſet forth by the aucthoritie of kyng Henry the eyght.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">31 The tyme of ſeruice.</note> whether the ſeruice of the Churche be done at due and conuenient houres.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">32 Talkers in the Church</note> whether any haue vſed to common, iangle, and talke in the Churche, in the tyme of the prayer, readyng of the Homylye, preachyng, readyng, or declaring of the Scripture.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">33 Hereſies.</note> whether any haue wylfully mayntey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and defended any hereſies, errours, or falſe opinions, contrary to the fayth of Chriſt and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye Scripture.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21219:6"/>
Item, whether any he common dronkardes,<note place="margin">34 Dronkards</note> ſwearers, or blaſphemers of the name of God.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">35 Adulterers.</note> whether any haue committed adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye, fornication, or inceſt, or be common bawdes, or receyuers of ſuch euill perſons, or vehemently ſuſpected of any of the premiſſes.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin"> 36 Brawlers.</note> whether any be brawlers, ſlaunderers, chyders, ſcolders, and ſowers of diſcorde betwene one perſon and another.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">37 Sorcerers.</note> whether you knowe any that do vſe charmes, ſorcerye, enchauntmentes, inuocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, circles, witchcraftes, ſouthſaying, or any lyke craftes or imaginations inuented by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll, and ſpeciallye in the tyme of womens tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayle.</p>
            <p>Item, whether the Churches, Pulpittes,<note place="margin">38 Pulpittes.</note> and other neceſſaryes apperteynyng to the ſame, be ſufficiently repayred, and yf they be not, in whoſe default the ſame is.</p>
            <p>Item, whether you knowe any,<note place="margin">39 Reſorters to other Churches.</note> that in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of theyr owne pariſhe Churche, do reſort to any other Churche.</p>
            <p>Item, whether any Inholders,<note place="margin">40 Inholders.</note> or Alehouſe kepers, do vſe commonly to ſell meate and drinke in the tyme of common prayer, preachyng, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng of the Homylyes or Scripture.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21219:7"/>
Item,<note place="margin">41 Diuorſe.</note> whether you knowe any to be marryed within the degrees prohibited by the lawes of God, or that be ſeperated or diuorſed without the degrees prohibited by the lawe of God, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any ſuche haue marryed agayne.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">42 Priuie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractes.</note> whether you knowe any to haue made priuie contractes of Matrimonie, not callyng two or mo wytneſſes thervnto, nor hauyng ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the conſent of theyr parentes.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">43 Banes.</note> whether they haue maryed ſolempnly, the banes not fyrſt lawfully aſked.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">44 Executou<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</note> whether you knowe any Executours or adminiſtratours of dead mens goodes, which do not duely beſtowe ſuche of the ſayde goodes as were geuen and bequeathed, or appoynted to be diſtributed among the poore people, repayryng of hygh wayes, fyndyng of poore ſcollers, or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying of poore maydens, or ſuche other lyke cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable deedes.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">45 Images.</note> whether you knowe any that kepe in theyr houſes vndefaced, and Images, Cables, Pictures, payntynges, or other monumentes of fayned and falſe miracles, pilgrimages, ydolatry and ſuperſtition, and do adore them, and ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye ſuche as haue ben ſet vp in Churches, Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelles, or Oratories.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">46 Bookes.</note> what bookes of Gods Scripture you
<pb facs="tcp:21219:7"/>haue deliuered to be burnt, or otherwyſe deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and to whom ye haue deliuered the ſame.</p>
            <p>Item, what brybes the accuſers, promoters,<note place="margin">47 Brybes.</note> perſecuters, Eccleſiaſticall iudges, and other the Commiſſioners appoynted within the ſeuerall Dioceſſe of this Realme, haue receyued by them ſelues or other, of thoſe perſons whiche were in trouble, apprehended, or impryſoned for Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
            <p>Item, what goodes, moueable landes, fees,<note place="margin">48 Loſſe of goodes.</note> offices, or promotions, hath ben wrongfully ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away in the time of Queene Maries raigne, <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>om any perſon whiche fauoured the Religion <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>we ſet forth.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">49 Howe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye burnt</note> howe many perſons for Religion haue dyed by fyre, famine, or otherwyſe, or haue ben impriſoned for the ſame.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">50 Certificat of the dear</note> that you make a true preſentment of the number of all the perſons whiche dyed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n your pariſhes, ſithen the feaſt of Saint Iohn <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e Baptiſt, whiche was in the yere of our Lorde God a thouſande fyue hundreth fiftie and eyght, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nto the ſame feaſt laſt paſt. Makyng therein a playne diſtinct declaration, howe many men, women, and men chyldren the ſame were. And the names of the men.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">51 Secrete Maſſes.</note> whether ye knowe any man in your
<pb facs="tcp:21219:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>paryſhe, ſecretelye or in vnlawfull conuenticles, ſay or heare Maſſe, or any other ſeruice prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the lawe.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">52 Falſe ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours.</note> whether you knowe any perſon in your paryſhe, to be a flaunderer of his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, or a ſower of diſcorde betwene partie and partie, man and wyfe, parentes and their chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, or that hath inuented, bruted, or ſet foorth any rumours,<note place="margin">Vnlawfull bookes.</note> falſe and ſedicions tales, ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, or makers, bryngers, byers, ſellers, kepers, or conueyers of any vnlawfull bookes, whiche myght ſtirre or prouoke ſedition, or mayntayne ſuperſtitious ſeruice within this Realme, or an, aydours, counſaylours, procurers, or may<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners thervnto.</p>
            <p>Item, whether the Churche of your paryſhe be nowe vacant or no,<note place="margin">53 Patron. Tythes. Vacation.</note> who is the Patrone ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, howe longe it hath ben vacant, who doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue the tythes, oblations, and other commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties during the time of the vacation, and by what aucthoritie, and in what eſtate the ſayde Church is at this time, and howe long the Parſon or Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car hath had that Benefice.</p>
            <p>Item,<note place="margin">54 Minſtrelles.</note> whether any Minſtrelles, or any other perſons do vſe to ſyng or ſay any ſonges or dit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that be vyle or vncleane, and eſpecially in deriſion of any Godly order nowe ſet forth and eſtablyſhed.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21219:8"/>
               <add>Item, <note place="margin">55 Letanie in Engliſh.</note> whether the Letany in Engliſh with the Epiſtle and Goſpell which was by the Queenes-highneſſe proclamation willed to be read to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, were put in vſe in your Churches and if not, - who were the letters thereof.</add>
            </p>
            <p>
               <add>Item,<note place="margin">56 Diſtinct reading.</note> whether the Curates and miniſters doe lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurelie, plainely, and diſtinctly reade the publique prayers, Chapters and Homilies, as they ought to doe.</add>
            </p>
            <closer>God ſaue the Queene.</closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:21219:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:21219:9"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
